<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="help.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD HelpDocBook XML V4.1.2//EN"
          "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd"
[
    <!ENTITY % brandDTD SYSTEM "chrome://global/locale/brand.dtd" >
    %brandDTD;
    <!ENTITY % helpDocDTD SYSTEM "helpDoc.dtd" >
    %helpDocDTD;
]>

<article xmlns:html="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
  <artheader>
    <title>Creating Web Pages with &brandShortName;</title>
    <para>&brandShortName; lets you create your own web pages and publish them
      on the web. You don't have to know HTML to use &brandShortName;; it is
      as easy to use as a word processor.</para>
    <para>Toolbar buttons let you add lists, tables, images, links to other
      pages, colors, and font styles. You can see what your document will
      look like on the Web as you create it, and you can easily share your
      document with other users, no matter what type of browser or
      HTML-capable email program they use.</para>
    <author><firstname>R.J.</firstname><lastname>Keller</lastname></author>
    <copyright><year>2003-2004</year><holder>Contributors to the Nvu Help Project.</holder></copyright>
  </artheader>

  <sect1>
    <title>Starting a New Page</title>
    
    <sect2>
    <title>Creating a New Page</title>
    
    <para>&brandShortName; is an HTML (Hypertext Markup Language) editor that
      allows you to create and edit web pages. &brandShortName; is a
      <html:em>WYSIWYG</html:em> (What You See Is What You Get) editor, so you can
      display how your page will look to the reader as you're creating
      it. It is not necessary for you to know HTML, since most of the basic
      HTML functions are available as commands from the toolbars and
      menus.</para>

    <para>&brandShortName; also lets you edit the HTML source if you want. To
      view or edit the HTML source code, open the View menu, and choose HTML
      Source, or click the &lt;HTML&gt; Source tab in the Edit Mode toolbar
      at the bottom of the &brandShortName; window.</para>

    <para>To create a web page, use one of the methods described below.  Once
      you've started a page, you can add and edit text just as you would in
      a word processor.</para>

    <para><html:strong>To create a new page in &brandShortName;</html:strong>:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Click the New button in &brandShortName;'s toolbar.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><html:strong>To start from an HTML file stored on your local
      drive</html:strong>:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Open the Window menu and choose &brandShortName;. You see the
        &brandShortName; window.</listitem>

      <listitem>Open the File menu and choose Open File. You see the Open HTML
        File dialog box.</listitem>

      <listitem>On your local drive, locate the file that you want to edit.</listitem>

      <listitem>Click Open to display the specified file in a &brandShortName;
        window.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para><html:strong>To edit a web page</html:strong>:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Open &brandShortName;</listitem>
      
      <listitem>Click on File menu and choose
        Open Web Location. You will see the Open Web Location dialog box.</listitem>
      
      <listitem>Type in the URL of the page to edit (for example,
        <tt>http://www.mozilla.org</tt>) and click Create button. You will see
        the page displayed in &brandShortName;.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para><html:strong>Tip</html:strong>: In the &brandShortName; window you can
      quickly open the most recent file you've been working on by opening
      the File menu, choosing Recent Pages, and then selecting the file you
      want from the list.</para>

    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
    <title>Tabs - Editing Multiple Documents</title>
    
    <para>&brandShortName; allows you to edit multiple documents at the same
      time. Rather than to shift from one window to another for editing more
      than one document, &brandShortName; offers the feature of
      <strong>Tabs</strong>. More than one document can be opened at the
      same time with &brandShortName; in the same window but in different
      tabs.</para>
    
    <para>Tabs can be opened using either <kbd>Ctrl+T</kbd> or by choosing
      Create in: <html:em>New Tab</html:em> in the New file open dialog. Even with
      multiple tabs open, each is handled independently. Each document's
      state is indicated, i.e. if it is modified and needs saving by a
      red-floppy icon on the corresponding tab.</para>
    
    </sect2>
    
    <sect2>
    <title>Saving and Browsing Your New Page</title>
    
    <para>You can save &brandShortName; documents in HTML or text-only
      format.  Saving a document in HTML format preserves the document's
      formatting, such as text styles (for example, bold or italic), tables,
      links, and images. Saving a document in text-only format removes all
      the HTML tags but preserves the document's text.</para>
      
    <para>To save a document as an HTML file:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Open the File menu and choose Save or click the Save button
        on the Composition toolbar.<html:br/><html:br/>
        
        If you haven't already given your page a title, &brandShortName;
        prompts you to do so. &brandShortName; displays the page title in the
        browser window's title bar when you view the page in the browser. The
        document's page title also appears in your list of bookmarks if you
        bookmark the page.<html:br/><html:br/>
        
        &brandShortName; then prompts you to enter a filename and specify
        the location where you want to save the file. Make sure you preserve
        the .html extension in the filename.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>To change the filename or location of an existing HTML file:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Choose Save As and select a different filename or
        location.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para>When you save a page in &brandShortName;, all parts of the page
      (the HTML, images and other files, such as sound files and style
      sheets), are saved locally on your hard drive. If you only want to
      save the HTML part of the page, you must change the &brandShortName;
      preference for saving pages. See <html:a
      href="#composer_preferences">&brandShortName; Preferences</html:a> for more
      information on changing &brandShortName;'s setting for saving
      pages.</para>
    
    <para>If an image location is absolute (starts with "http://") and you
      are connected to the Internet, you will still see that image in the
      document in &brandShortName; and Navigator. However, if the image
      location is relative to the page location (starts with "file:///"),
      then you won't see the image in the local version of the document.</para>
    
    <para>To save a document as a text-only file:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Open the File menu and choose Export to Text.</listitem>

      <listitem>Enter the filename and specify the location where you want to save
        the file.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    
    <para><html:strong>Note</html:strong>: Images do not appear in documents saved in
      the text-only format.</para>
    
    <para><html:strong>Tip</html:strong>: You can choose Revert from the File menu to
      retrieve the most recently saved copy of the document in which you're
      working. Keep in mind that your current changes will be lost.</para>
    
    <para>To view your page in a browser window in order to test your
      links:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>Open the File menu and choose Browse Page (or click Browse in
        the Composition toolbar). If you have not yet saved your document,
        &brandShortName; prompts you to enter a page title, filename, and
        location.  The &brandShortName; window remains open behind the new
        Navigator window.</listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>
  
  <sect1>
    <title>Formatting Your Web Pages</title>
    
    <sect2>
    <title>Formatting Paragraphs, Headings, and Lists</title>
    </sect2>

  </sect1>
</article>
